Right, so this quick video really on OTC and exchange structure or the differences between the two,
I've actually been meaning to make this video for quite a while, so just get straight into it.
So when we're referring to OTC or exchange, to keep it extremely simple, it's the way, it's basically the rules under which assets trade.
All right, so in FX, OTC, the specific rules I guess.
or custom to trade FX.
And then in an exchange, there's a different set of rules or customs to trade exchange-based assets.
I will say here, though, any financial product in the world can trade on OTC.
So it can be traded over-the-counter.
Think of over-the-counter as literally just buying something from a shopkeeper.
Your transaction is between you and the owner of the shop.
right that's that's where the transaction taking place just between you and the over the
shop owner of the shop over the counter literally that's the meaning of OTC so the two
parties in a OTC way of trading or OTC transaction is between the I guess the
you can say the buyer and then of course the seller or the the the one that's
providing you the service
versus the customer
because the customer can sell
to a service provider as well
now ultimately you call that
bilateral trading
right so
participants or the way of trading
and OTC will be bilateral
between two parties
right now the way that applies to FX
is you go directly to a
dealer
is to with us
this is our brokers
but in the Interbank
market, you go directly to a dealer and the dealer basically gives you liquidity, right?
What they do with that liquidity is up to them. So here you have a, let me just pull up a pen.
So here you have a dealer, it's door with your bank, right? They have one client. Let's just say it's
me. And then they have another client. Let's just say it's client two, all right?
now when I place a trade with them or when I place a trade really I'm asking DB for quotes
and the transaction is between us too okay so if I'm buying the euro and I'm selling the
US dollars the transactions between me and Deutsche Bank now I've just bought the euro I've
sold the US dollars Deutsche Bank have then brought the US dollars off me what they decide to
do with that is their choice they can hold it they can filter off much it inside for
client in-house or they can of course filter off into the broader market so just hedge
themselves or take on the risk that's their choice that's their risk because you know it has
nothing to do with my transaction so it's bilateral trading between two points that's OTC now in
an exchange you essentially call it multilateral so rather than my trade also it's important to say
here that if me and you whoever's listening to the video of me and you wanted to do it over-the-counter
transaction, guess what, that's OTC transaction, right? It's between me and you, nobody else.
Of course, the risk is that you default. So let's say we're trading something physical, right,
and I buy a car of you. Ultimately, if you failed to give, like, send over that car to me,
my risk was that you're going to, you know, you're my risk, basically. So if you're ever trading on
OTC, your counterparty risk is against whoever you're trading with, and it's usually going to be
directly with your broker.
Even if your broker says they don't take, so you're trading on ECN, or if your broker says
that they don't, they're not a dealing desk, they are still acting as principle, right?
So you're buying, they're selling to you, and then they may, if they're a good broker,
they may go and hedge that sell whatever they bought off you, if they're a good broker.
but again most of these brokers because a lot of people don't trade large amounts
retail effects I'm talking about they don't trade large amounts maybe they're trading
over leveraged brokers on nowadays retail brokers are probably going to just be sitting
on the flow they're going to internalize it at best they'll match it in-house with another
client okay because first of all is just to keep it really simple it's to send flow
off to a I say a liquidity provider at a bank
they won't accept anything beneath a million, anything, right?
So that's going to be, maybe, you know, if, let's say,
a broker doesn't want to take on risk, they'll, I shouldn't really be talking about it,
but if a broker doesn't want to take on risk,
they might take, you know, 5,000 orders that come in over the last 10 seconds
or something, aggregate it, and then go ahead and hedge it, right?
If they don't want to take the opposite side, or if they can't find in-house counterparties.
But, you know, if there's 5,000 orders come in,
they can definitely match a few together.
anyway so why are so a central counterparty exchange based trading let's have a look at
that multilateral is essentially there so here's the table right you can have
your central counterparty the referee you umpire the fucking whatever you want to call it
now whenever I place a trade okay so let's say I'm buying
you know, 5 million euros on an exchange-based system,
I could essentially be getting filled by 5 million divided by 1,000,
5,000 other participants, because the minimum execution sides would be 1,000, right?
0.01 lots.
So this could be 5 million, it could be broken down into 5,000, 0.01 lots.
and in theory it could be matched with 5,000 1K sell trades
whilst I'm buying 5 million euros, or it could be much directly
with a 5 million seller I could buy it.
But the point I'm making here is my trade could be against 5,000 other people
whereas in OTC, you trades directly with the principal, with the dealer, basically, or you're broke up.
Now, essentially, think about if I was buying 5 million euros of 5,000 people, right, so 1,000 each, I think that's right, when it came to settling my trade, so when it came to actually paying them, let's say the U.S.D, I brought the euros in, and I'd have to go individually to 5,000 people and collect my money, it's going to take fucking time, right? So the central counterparty does it.
but in this instance the central counterpart if you want to go trade at this guy's table or the
exchanges table you have to follow a strict set of rules right that's going to guarantee you
essentially transparency especially in pricing and available equity so the CP the central
counterpart is going to be overlooking all transactions making sure really that there's no dodgy
shit going on although it will happen in terms of spoofing
which is completely beside the point.
It's just a much more transparent,
but yet complex way of executing your trades.
It's much more safer as well.
But it's important to note,
so how I just said you can go individually to 5,000 people,
collecting money, settle it, takes a long time.
Rather than that happening,
my trade is settled with the counterparty.
And then, of course, this counterparty never takes on risk.
That's not their job.
They're not a dealer.
They're not essentially even a broker.
They're a referees sitting in the middle, making sure everybody gets a piece of the pie or a fear equal piece of the pie.
So you have a good example, I guess, is if you brought something from eBay on an OTC, you brought something, I sell you something, the transaction between me and you.
Okay, so you've paid me.
I haven't sent the item off.
Your risk was that I didn't send my item, right?
So your risk on our OTC, eBay transaction is between me, the seller and you, the buyer.
Whereas on an exchange, you're actually going to send your money to the counterparty in the middle, which is eBay.
I'm going to send my package to eBay.
You're going to expect your package from eBay.
And I'm going to expect my money from eBay.
So eBay's in the middle.
You send your money.
I send my package.
eBay sends you
my package and of course
eBay sends me your money
right so the middleman here
the exchange eBay
make sure that the trades
are settled right so your settlement
risk or counterparty risk is with
the central counterparty
that in essence
facilitates multilateral
trade okay
another key point here is the central
counterparty on an exchange
sorry on an exchange based system
there's only one order book because everybody's sitting on the same table right banks are at the same table
um i'm at the same table all the clients are at the same table hedge funds whatever as long as they
are part of the exchange they're sitting in the same table okay so let's just say this five million was
not a market order it's a limit buy order it goes and sits in the book everybody can see it all right
um and let's just say i'm trying to buy five million on a limit order and then of course
you here are looking at the limit order book,
okay, a single book, you can see that,
okay, there's an order of $5 million here.
You can immediately hit the bid and sell
and access $5 million worth of liquidity.
It's yours. It's there.
It's not quote-driven.
This is order-driven prices.
Essentially, whatever prices you're seeing on an exchange
are exactly where supply meets demand, right?
The equilibrium point.
It's always going to be the thinnest point in liquidity,
but that's where it is.
Whereas again, on the OTC system, it's not order driven, it's actually quote driven.
So an OTC transaction, I'm here selling my car, all right, I'm selling my car.
I decide what price to sell it out, right?
I decide.
I can actually change my prices as well.
The same applies with FX.
Docia Bank is providing quotes to their customers, not order driven quotes, not
guaranteed quotes, but just quotes.
Your broker, if you go look in the execution
policy, all they're providing you is
quotes. They're not guaranteed. That's why you can get
slipped and re-quoted
with these larger banks.
It used to be the case anyway, where
last look was a prevalent thing.
So, one hand,
you have central counterparty, it facilitates
loads of loads of transactions at once, so you can find
liquidity, it's a limit order book,
driven pricing, much more transparent.
Whatever ticks
price takes,
up and down or recorded actually on the exchange now that data how the central counterpart makes
the money is they'll sell that data all right so um the CCP can actually let's just say this is
showing you the price of uh let's use a real example this is showing you the price of nasdaq all right
which is uh an index of a hundred of the hundred biggest tech companies in the u.s and think i don't
We trade the NASDAQ, right?
But that's the index that's trading on this exchange, and it's a futures contract.
This data is going to be replicated by your broker or by a derivative contract.
So this contract just simply reflects the price of NASDAQ.
That's all it does.
When you buy this contract, it's called a CFD.
It literally just reflects the price of NASDAQ.
In other words, your broker is taking these prices, okay?
and essentially reflecting it in a contract, right?
That's called the CFD.
Now, the CCP, the central counterparty,
they will charge people, right, to access this data, right?
That's how that essentially they're making their money.
And they also charge these guys sitting at the table a monthly fee or a yearly fee.
But it's important to, I'll say this, a lot of these brokers,
they have these CFD contacts, but it says on the contract,
these prices are indicative, right?
And the prices are going to be slightly, slightly different.
So maybe like one point different
from the actual futures contract of NASDAQ, all right?
Ultimately, what it results in is these guys,
these brokers that are copying the prices of NASDAQ,
they get to sidestep the fees that the central counterparties
will charge because they are going to charge a lot.
They're making, it's really good data.
They're providing extremely transparent.
It's true supply and demand backed by orders.
so the data costs a lot
so OTC
bilateral exchange
multi-lateral
all right
single order book driven
exchange
so it's order driven
quotes or order-driven prices
and then OTC is
quote driven
okay
in other words
you know if I'm buying
at the price
quoted by DB
doesn't mean you're going to
guarantee you're guaranteed
to get filled by the time
my order reaches them
they could deny the quote
they could change the price
and give
me a re-quote. It could simply, what could also happen is someone else took that liquidity
before my order reached. Deutsche Bank's already started to move their prices higher whilst I'm
buying, and I get slipped. Right. It's in a fast market. Now, the products that trade on exchanges
are some derivative contracts, right? So, so futures, options, stocks, shares, same thing.
the EES, so indices, contracts, so the ES Mini, S&P 500 Mini, these all trade on exchanges.
So there's kind of a limited, limited finite amount of assets that trade on exchanges,
but OTC is any financial product, okay?
Now, you might be asking, you know, or I would ask myself,
why wouldn't everybody trade on the CCP?
It's more transparent, it's more fair.
You get access to liquidity that's actually there.
right there's no re-quoting um you can get slipped but there's no re-quoting um it basically
it's much more transparent right it's fair environment your counterparty risk is just with a CCP
who is never taking on risk right so when i'm buying five million euros and the CCP is
finding me a seller at no point the CCP is going to take on that five million in risk right
So they are actually extremely reliable, okay, to give your money, essentially.
Whereas DB, I buy 5 million euros of them and they sell me the euros and they buy my
USD off me.
What if, whilst this transaction was going on, right?
So I brought euros and they brought the USD off me.
What if the value of USD just plummeted?
right these guys now have before the trade was settled as well i should say so i've brought the two
million euros or five million euros doesn't mean you get it in an instant okay it's settled in two
days that is called fx transactions will have this on their policies it's basically the transaction
is settled in two days so if i buy five million right now my my transaction i'll get the actual
money if i wanted to access it in physical cash uh if i'm trading on the internet
bank especially um in two days okay now if that's the case right and i've brought five million euros
i've paid maybe yeah i've paid db uh five million euros worth of dollars and at that time the
usd plummet so much so just just think about what's happened here that db took on and brought
us dollars and the u.s dollars plummeting so much so that db is not and now has uh
liabilities that are greater than their assets, right?
So they're owning, their own US dollars,
but the value of those US dollars are plummeting,
so they're worth nothing and they're in a big fat hole, right?
How are they then?
And basically the total value of their assets,
including everything that they have,
the buildings were valued,
all the other derivative contracts that they have,
plus this US dollar that's plummeting,
all the, you know, MS, MBSs that they hold everything.
The total value of the assets,
by maybe even a small percentage
has just dropped beneath their liabilities.
They now can't settle
my 5 million euro trade in two days.
Right? So again, the counterparty risk is real.
In 2015, the FXCM, a broker,
they went,
basically they had a long,
they had a short exposure on the Swiss franc.
The S&B basically just pulled the floor.
No, they didn't pull the floor.
they stopped
suppressing the value of
the Swiss franc
and essentially the Swiss franc
he had a big flash crash
right the USD Swiss franc
dropped massively like a thousand or
3,000 pips in a single day
literally in minutes I think
yeah so FXEM had a
$300 million hole that day
right so in other words
some of their clients were long
sorry some of their clients were long
Swiss franc against the US dollar
so on the US
S.D. Swiss franc, right? They were short. They were long, this, they were short the
USD, so it's a short position. And FXM were now long USD Swiss franc, and this is what
the pair was doing, right? They had a $300 million hole, but they had clients who were massively
up on this short position. They couldn't pay them out because they didn't have enough money.
Their liabilities were now bigger than the assets, right? But they had to go
don't get a loan from a bank for 300 million, right? So counterparty risk is very real. It's true.
It exists. That's why you don't keep a lot of your money with any of these shitty little brokers.
Do it's your bank a less like its default because they're just my high, they capitalized well.
But, you know, in 2008, Lehman Brothers collapsed. So these banks aren't indestructible. I forgot the
over word, right? They're not immune to risk. Anyway, so if that's the case, these structures,
one's much, much more better
and the other one's more risky
why would anyone trade on OTC
well first of all
it's like custom
right
when the FX market started out
that's where
there was an OTC structure that the banks
were dealing with each other on and still do to this day
it's just custom right
but secondly
it's anonymous
if me and you do a transaction
nobody else has to know about it
On an exchange, on an exchange, the transaction is recorded, essentially.
Right.
Now, also, the exchange-based trading has very strict rules, right?
You have to abide by the rules.
But what about, and really, those rules are supporting or facilitating trade
amongst competitive trading or competitive participants, right?
I want liquidity quick, I want it there right now.
you know it's much more I guess accustomed for speculative trading and competitive trading
whereas OTC especially affects the the participants aren't necessarily speculative they might
actually have different needs I am because OTC is much more relaxed in terms of regulation and
rule based trading it's not even rule based trading it's principle based trading we trade based on these
general customs that we uh been trading on for the last
100 years or however long it is, 50 years, we're going to stick by them. It gives them more
flexibility to bend the rules, bend the prices. Not even bend the prices, just provide solutions
for different types of clients. So if a client want to do a specific type of FX deal,
they could build essentially a solution for that, right, or provide a solution for that. In an exchange
where it's trading, you don't get to do that. It's just the rules of the exchange or the rules you abide
by right so yeah that's really the main reason it's much more flexible and you
can have multinational corporations trading on OTC you can have hedge fund
managers trying to trade overseas you can have speculative trading it's important
to know that they are I guess you could call it like an exchange models in
FX which is LMAX all right so LMAX are basically here
all right they run a table the banks sit at a table all right and the bank's plug in actual quotes
so here's the order book of the table the bank is plugging in actual quotes in the form of
limit orders all right and then you are also plugging in limit orders or you can take the liquidity
as well and again let's just say you're a client that's buying okay your trade goes to the limit order
book, right? There's no recourse because it's order driven. If there's liquidity there, you take
it. Obviously, then LMAX, essentially it goes to the order book. You're trying to buy the liquidity
that this bank again, let's just call it Deutsche Bank. This Deutsche Bank has a set limit. You're buying
that set limit up, all right, at the top of the book, let's just say. Your order, let's just say
again there's a million limit order sell you're buying a million right the way it's done is your
order goes to try and take this right but what actually happens is you buy one million of elmax
lmax simultaneously go and get the one million from dosha bank and your risk is with elmx not with
do you should make so it's a exchange based trading there's a single order book
um it's order driven prices so it acts as an exchange but it's basically
called it mtf a multilateral trading facility all right and then you have I guess
ECNs which are read these ones are good ECNs like hotspot all right again
they're just the third party aggregator that has deals they have deals
And I guess, yeah, basically I have credit lines with the interbank market, right?
So with one bank, two bank, three bank, four bank, they're connected through something
called APIs, all right, the individual connections, right?
So hotspot, you'll be taking this liquidity, pouring it into essentially an ECN.
And in this ECN, you can access this as well, okay.
liquidity from their liquidity providers that they can access is also plugged into the
ECM gives you relatively tight spreads it's anonymous order routing hotspot do not
take on this risk they just facilitate trade again right the third-party
ego gear and then you know your brokers are doing this they'll be connected to a
company like hotspot maybe two three hotspot it might be FX all
Korenx all right they might be connected to all three you're placing a trade
the broker's filling you that's it you're placing a trade your broker's filling you what they do
with that you know what they do with by filling you what they do with the liquidity that they're taking
on is their choice really but they can take on the risk again they can most of the time they can
take on the risk because people are shit if they don't want to take on the risk they'll just
match it in-house with another client right this guy's buying this guy's selling all right much them up
2. We don't have to send it through to HotSpot or Koronex. If you're trading on MT4,
these guys are quoting prices individually to your broker. Your broker is taking those
quotes and actually putting it in manually into MT4 through the back office. Whereas C-trader
directly runs the quotes from these guys. It runs the quotes on your platform that you see
directly from the third party aggregate is
the broker's connected to it
and then you're connected I guess
through C-trader, we're onto your broker's server.
Now when you place a trade on C-trader,
it hits your broker's server
at the price quoted by these third parties
and essentially
basically the broker can fill you
and hedge it with these third parties
or they can just fill you and internalize the flow
but at no point does the broker have control over the prices.
That's the key thing.
So it's slightly more transparent, right?
It's not completely because the broker can still trade against you,
but only at the price is quoted by the real market.
All right.
So you have MTFs, you have ECNs, and you have this retail model shit.
OTC exchange is simply that.
OTC is good, flexible.
anonymous really you're going to get some
some of the dodgy practices on OTC
because it's hard to regulate it
it's really hard to find out what a transaction
or what kind of transaction happened just between two parties
but I would say you know these main banks these main
dealers they're tier one banks they abide by the
global FX code
it's just hard to enforce it
but anyway if you have any questions
I don't know